Matsumoto Productions
and Nippon ATG
SHURA
(DEMONS)
Based on "Kamikakete
Sango Taisetsu" by...
Namboku Tsuruya and
Shuji Ishizawa
Photography by
Tatsuo Suzuki
Art by Setsu Asakura
Lights by Yoshio Unno
Edited by Toshie Iwasa
With...
Katsuo Nakamura
Juro Kara
Yasuko Sanjo
Masao Imafuku
Tamotsu Tamura
Hideo Kanze
Kappei Matsumoto
Shinshi Amano
Hatsuo Yamatani
Yusuke Minami
Written and directed by
Toshio Matsumoto
English subtitles by
Don Kenny
Open the gate!
Open it!
Oboshi! Sir!
Koman, let me in.
It's Gengobe.
Koman, open up!
Koman, what's wrong?
Get a hold of yourself!
You scared me.
I almost pushed this
big pin right...
through my ear.
Was it a dream?
A dream?
You were groaning
about something.
What was it about?
It was a very strange dream.
You were lying...
over there with your...
face on the floor.
Just a dream!
You're mean.
What happened to me?
It was nothing.
I've forgotten it already.
You're awfully mean.
Come on, tell me.
Don't worry,
maybe it wasn't you at all.
So you were with some
other girl, weren't you?
Dreams are the mirror
of the true heart!
Tell me just who she was, Gengobe!
Don't talk foolishly.
You are the only girl
I care for, anywhere.
Is that really true?
I don't lie to you.
What is this tattoo?
"Godairiki"
"Godairiki is a pledge
of eternal love."
It makes me blush to say it, but
it is a Godairiki love pledge tattoo.
An oath to never be
touched by another man.
For whom?
You're cruel to ask.
It is for you.
Look closely.
Who else would it be?
For me?
That is a lie.
You're so cruel.
It hurts, so this must
not be a dream.
Even if it's a dream,
I want to live for love alone.
Gengobe, please make me your wife.
Koman.
Who is it?
It's Hachiemon.
I've come home.
You're early.
I came fast with good news.
How is everyone at home?
Very well.
But, sir,
What has happened here?
I sold everything to
pay my debts.
Not the hanging
scroll by Eitoku!
Yes, that too.
But it was an heirloom.
I know.
But, that still wasn't enough.
The landlord comes day and night,
demanding more rent.
I can't even sleep.
Are you in your
right mind, sir?
That doesn't matter.
You have no right
to question me.
Hachiemon.
Have you ever heard the proverb,
"everything in nothing?"
No, I haven't.
It means that all is
in a lack of everything.
It's full of meaning.
Do you mean to say that
the vixen in there...
Is what you call
something in nothing?
What do you mean
calling me a vixen?!
I've become his wife
this very day.
What?
As I'm Gengobe's wife
you mustn't talk to me like that!
This is a crazed vixen.
You shut up and
get out of here!
Gengobe, say something!
Gengobe!
Oh, how cruel.
So your promise was a lie?
Koman, I think you
should go for now.
Oh, you are against
me now too...
See now? Get out!
I won't forget this!
Don't push me so much!
And don't come back!
Gengobe, you have made
me very sad today.
Don't look so glum.
With Koman here, even this
empty house is like a garden,
but your glum face
makes me nervous.
Are you serious, sir?
What if I am?
How cruel! At first I believed
you dedicated to the vendetta,
but you spend your money
on prostitutes,
while your man Tokuemon has set
himself up as priest of Aizome Temple...
in Yotsuya, and is trying
to gather the money you lost...
in order to get you back
in good with Oboshi,
so you can
be part of the revenge.
And then when you some forty men
take your own lives after it's done,
I plan to do the same.
Here I come back and
find you with that...
famous geisha Koman
of Nakacho, for whom...
you have sold all your
household goods.
You can't be sane!
Do you still call
yourself a samurai?
Is this the end of Soemon Funakura,
the retainer of the Enya family?
You are probably angry
with me for saying this,
but please give Koman up.
I beg of you!
Are you finished? You're a good actor!
A most amusing show!
What?!
I have my reasons.
Don't worry yourself.
You mean this is to
fool the enemies?
Of course!
If that's true, I'm very happy.
Please forgive my rudeness.
Now you sound like Soemon of
the Enya family again.
Don't talk so loud.
The walls have ears!
I am the poor samurai Gengobe Satsuma
to the outside world right now.
Yes, Gengobe, sir, and
I have good news.
Look at this.
100 ryo?!
The men at home all got together
to thank you for past favors.
Some sold fields and others borrowed
to make this 100 ryo for you.
With this you must pay
the government money you lost...
and become one with Oboshi and the others
as an honorable samurai once more.
Please accept this
for that purpose.
Is that the way it is?
Thank you so much.
I'm out of breath!
What is it now?!
I forgot something
very important.
Oh, here it is!
I'm so careless!
Gengobe!
Koman doesn't want to
go back to Nakamachi.
I have to talk to
Hachiemon just now.
Yes, I understand.
I have to go
as I have a customer.
A geisha has to be nice even if
she doesn't like her customer.
Sorry I bothered you.
100 ryo! I had given up on ever
getting so much together again.
You did a good job.
Thanks again.
It makes me happy just
to see you so happy.
Please go early tomorrow
morning and get your name...
on the list with
Oboshi and the others.
Yes, I'll do just that.
This cloth is perfect
for wrapping the money.
I can't thank you enough.
"An hour later..."
Pardon my intrusion.
Who is it?
Sangoro of Sasanoya.
I've important business
with you, sir.
Sorry to bother you so late.
Thanks for your
patronage, Gengobe.
What is it?
Koman asked me to give
you this letter.
Please read it and
go see her.
You're lucky to have a woman
so in love with you.
She does seem to have something
important to talk to me about.
Not tonight, sir. Have you
forgotten what you just said?
He cannot possibly
go tonight.
So just get off
with the other rats.
Hachiemon is right.
I'll stay home tonight.
Now you are talking
like yourself, sir.
If you let things go, you may
get yourself killed for it.
Sir, you are too young
to know real love.
Are you going to let
poor Koman die?
Then you'll find me your enemy
and have a fight on your hands.
All joking aside, sir,
didn't you know that...
a Kono samurai came to
pay Koman's debts?
I heard she had such a customer,
but didn't...
know he was going to
pay and take her away.
Why didn't she tell me?
She was here twice.
Oh, I see what it was.
She came here to try
to find some way to tell you,
but was too shy
to come out and say it.
After all a geisha is
for buying and selling.
She kept quiet so as not to
cause you undue worry. I'm sure.
As soon as she got
home from here,
she began crying and
throwing things.
Before long that Kono
samurai will be there.
I shudder to think of
what she must be going through now.
Poor girl.
Please go and console
her a little now, sir.
Sir, you must be
strong against...
the tricks of that vixen.
You're right.
But why is Koman acting
that way just now?
Then, sir, is it all
right to go back...
and tell Koman that
Gengobe is cold and...
cruel and that she
should forget him?
That's just what we
want you to tell her.
If you do that, sir,
you will never see
Koman again, and won't...
be welcome at the shop.
So I have to go make
the girl cry, do I?
Wait, Sangoro!
What?
You're impatient.
I'll go with you.
That's the way!
Have you changed your
mind so soon, sir?
Oh, please hear me,
and stay here tonight!
You shut up and watch
the house for me.
No, I won't.
Are you trying to make
your master angry?
No, not me!
Then stay!
But I don't have anything
to give the landlord...
if he comes for the rent.
There're enough
umbrellas for that.
No, there aren't.
Pay him with this hair pin.
It was made by Goto.
But, sir, must you?
Let's go!
Follow me.
Oh, dear!
He must really be in
love with that vixen!
What shall I do?!
And with all his debts too.
Even made by Goto, will one of a pair
satisfy the landlord?
Oh, the 100 ryo!
Master!
"A tea house in Fukagawa."
- No, I won't give in!
- Now, don't get excited.
After all I've given her,
why does Koman reject Banemon?!
Because I don't like you.
Don't like me?
Listen, Koman.
You're my sister, but I won't
let you be so selfish!
I don't like him and
I won't go with him!
I'm the one that signed
for the loan,
so don't be rough with her
or I'll be in trouble.
Banemon promises to let you live as
you like, so if you say yes...
you will save you and me both
from a lot of worry and trouble.
And me as a samurai!
She just won't listen
to anything I say.
Have another drink
and be calm.
Drink? A good idea!
Pour for me!
Don't be so angry.
Koman must have some
reason for refusing.
Torazo, you must know.
Tell me her reason!
It is nothing unusual.
It is just that Koman has a lover.
Is he a samurai or
a townsman?
He is a no-good ronin
named Gengobe.
I don't know why
she likes him.
He is a beggar!
But he was originally
a man of position,
even so he doesn't
mind that I'm a geisha.
He still wants me.
But he was already a penniless beggar
before he fell for you.
That's the way they talk.
I feel sick.
I feel even worse.
If I only had money.
Your Gengobe could never get together
100 ryo, no matter how he tried,
but I have it right here
to pay right now.
Think which of us can
take care of you best.
He is right.
The 100 ryo is most important.
He is a very good
offer, Koman.
Right! Forget that
man and take Banemon.
Be my wife!
No, I won't!
Look at this!
It's the Godairiki pledge to never
let another man touch me.
My heart is locked against
any man except Gengobe.
You'll not open it
with your gold key!
I am Samurai Gengobe's wife.
So you refuse me?
Yes, with all my heart.
And this is all
Gengobe's fault.
Damn! I'll kill him!
Careful, Gengobe may
be listening.
Then tell him to
get 100 ryo!
Where'd he get it?!
He'd never even get
together a few shu!
He'd run off with his
tail between his legs.
Just a minute!
I am that Gengobe Satsuma!
Oh, Gengobe,
I'm glad you are here.
So this is.
I told you not to gossip!
We heard all you said!
Who do you think you are calling
a beggar?! Watch your tongues!
But I didn't.
You won't get off
so easy as that!
What'll we do with them, sir?
You people.
Please forgive us.
I beg of you!
I, Gengobe, will now
pay Koman's debts.
100 ryo in pure gold!
That's right.
And I receive Koman in return.
How's that?!
Who said Gengobe couldn't get
together even a few shu?!
Don't make me laugh!
I've served him for
some time and know...
that he always has
100 ryo in his pocket.
Come on, Koman!
Then I will.
I'm so happy, Gengobe!
What have you done, sir?!
That 100 ryo was gathered so you could
participate in the vendetta.
Where're you going, sir?
I mustn't be seen here.
I'm going.
But, sir, doesn't it
make you angry...
to hear them talking
about you like that?
It makes me mad.
Let's go in there!
Listen, Gengobe is here!
Oh, Gengobe,
I'm glad you are here.
So this is.
I told you not to gossip!
We heard all you said!
Who do you think you are
calling this man a beggar?!
Don't make me laugh!
Who said Gengobe couldn't get
together even a few shus?
He always has 100 ryo
or so in his pocket.
Sangoro, don't talk so big.
As you said, sir, you can do
as you please with this woman.
I'm a beggar as you say and
have no right to stand in your way...
whatever you do with her.
What are you saying?
Where does that leave
Koman and me?
Gengobe, thanks for taking
care of me and my sister.
You have given us a very
good life all this time.
Tramping in like this,
I thought you'd have 100 ryo.
This is a real joke!
Chohachi, that goes
without saying.
He may have been a fine
samurai before, but...
now he's nothing compared to me,
Banemon of the Konos.
Oh, please, sir.
Say something back to him!
No, he's right.
Leave him alone.
So, ladies' man, money
and power has done it.
Pardon me.
Do you really mean
I must be his wife?
Be happy! Goodbye!
What're you doing?
How can I live after...
the man I love
has abandoned me?
There's nothing for her
to do but die.
Sir, you have
disappointed us!
Go ahead and die!
I'd be much obliged to
Gengobe if he let you.
Die if you like!
Koman, wouldn't you
rather be mine?
How horrible!
Let me go!
Don't be stupid!
Oh, Gengobe,
you're so very cruel!
Don't force me to
live in shame!
I live in the same shame.
Goodbye!
Farewell, until we
meet in that world.
Wait!
Do you really feel
that strongly?
Yes.
I, Gengobe, hereby pay
Koman's ransom debts.
But that's 100 ryo.
Right! 100 ryo!
Here is the 100 ryo, take it, and
I receive Koman in return!
It's 100 ryo in pure gold!
You can't judge a man
by the way he looks!
Just look at this!
This is the Gengobe
I, Sangoro, call my lord and master!
I'm a ronin,
but still a samurai.
I'm happy to meet you Banemon!
What's this?!
But first of all,
no one has any objections to
my ransoming Koman with this 100 ryo?
None at all.
Wait! I object!
What are you doing here?
I was afraid this is
what you would do.
And after I warned
and scolded you so.
Water spilled from
a bowl doesn't return.
But that 100 ryo was
gathered by those...
back home for you to
make a come back.
Shut up!
You don't know my heart!
Let's get better
acquainted, Banemon!
I would like to,
but I have a stomach-ache.
Wait, you samurai!
What a dull samurai!
Now all the tears are over,
I mean to make Koman my wife.
Come with me, Koman.
Oh, Gengobe,
you just make me so happy...
Oh, sir.
Please wait a moment.
What do you mean, wait?
It is true that you
paid Koman's ransom,
but unfortunately,
she has a husband.
Koman has a husband?!
Right, and unless she
breaks with him.
Is this true, Koman?
Answer me!
Who is the man?!
Well, he...
Sangoro, who is
Koman's husband?
It is me.
What? You?
Yes, I'm her husband,
and Koman is my wife.
I tried to find a patron for her.
You've been a good patron.
So the two of you have
worked together...
to lead me into this
deep situation?
You bastards!
Well, it isn't easy
to sit by and...
watch your own wife
with another man.
And, Koman,
did you fool me too?
I know you are mad,
but there were deep reasons.
Please believe my heart.
Shut up,
you stupid woman!
Shut up!
It was my mistake to
be bewitched by her,
but you are really
terrible to try...
to rob a man of his
property this way!
It's money, not duty
that keeps you alive!
You inhuman bastard!
Stop, Master, your life
is too important!
Don't try to stop me!
Endure this.
Please don't do it!
Come cut us down if you want to,
but remember that...
Koman is my legal wife,
not yours.
Cut away if you like,
it's your loss!
You and your beastly insults.
It's my sin to have
been born a woman.
Please forgive me,
and kill me now.
You filthy thing!
Get away from me!
Quiet!
You are inhuman!
But, Master, you must save
yourself from all this.
Think of yourself!
Don't kill them.
Let's go home.
Oh, Sangoro,
you are too cruel.
Oh, my poor heart.
Your woman's heart may
find it hard, but...
I have to get 100 ryo
no matter what to get...
my father to forgive
me and take me back.
Since he disowned me
ten years ago.
I was worried,
but it all came out alright.
Here is your 100 ryo.
Thanks. You all put
on a real good show.
There'll be some for
the rest of us?
Don't worry. Go on
and warm up some saké.
OK. I'll be home
waiting for you.
"Later the same night..."
Koman, you are
the only one I love.
Is that the truth?
I wouldn't lie...
What is this tattoo?
It is embarrassing to say, but...
it is a pledge to never
let another man touch me.
A pledge of love.
Love for whom?
Oh, you're cruel.
It is you.
Who else would it be?
We'll change it to
"Precious Sangoro."
It stings!
A sly rewrite!
But maybe she really
felt the original.
Stupid! She loves
only "precious" me!
You're awful!
Look at that!
And look at this!
What'll you do now?
But Gengobe must
be awful angry.
Did you fall for him
a little after all?
Don't be silly!
A geisha lives a life of lies.
But they say truth
Is born from lies.
Oh, Kikuno, you too?
You did put it on
pretty strong.
How can I live,
abandoned by my love?
And Gengobe overdid
the lover role too.
If I were him, I think I would have
been more careful with the gold.
This "gold" won't
get by me!
How's this?
You planned that!
Oh, you inhuman bastards!
Unfortunately, she has a husband.
It is me.
Don't be so glum.
You're scaring me.
I just feel uneasy.
You'll feel alright
after a good sleep.
I want to get this
money to my father...
and get him to take
me back as his son.
And you can show him
his grandson.
I wonder how our son is.
Let's go get him from
foster parents tomorrow.
Yes, and we'll live
together happily,
and find some new way
to make a living.
And I'll work too.
Oh, please,
make me feel warm.
Oh, damn!
Looks like I have to run.
That's the way!
And I fly into a check!
You got him!
How about it? Can you
get away now, Gengobe?
I'm done for!
Look, he's sleeping.
That's only natural, because
it's almost three a.m. already.
They make me nervous!
I'm getting excited too.
Let's go, Kikuno.
Not here!
In there then?
Oh, you!
We'll see you all later.
Damn them all!
So that leaves us two.
Well, let's go to bed too.
Guess we may as well.
Who is it? Inosuke?
"Several days later..."
"The place is now Yotsuya..."
Yes, I'm glad you
granted my request.
A blessing from the gods.
Since then, I became a priest and
have spent my time serving the gods.
But I never forget
my lord's revenge.
Enya's old retainers
loiter about here...
but the most pitiful
Is Soemon Funakura.
He didn't have the 100 ryo necessary
to become one of the revengers,
so I have done everything
I could to gather it for him,
but failed at every turn.
And now here you are offering
that amount for my use.
It must have been
difficult for you to raise.
Yes, we two worked
hard to make it.
You did a very good job!
I forgive you and take
you back as my son.
Thank you. Listen,
Koman, he forgave me!
Oh, I'm so happy.
I really thank you.
You must have endured
a lot too. Thank you.
Then do you approve
of us too?
Of course.
Sentaro took a fine bride.
Thank you so very much.
Congratulations.
Is that my grandson?
Yes. Have a good look at him.
What a lovely baby.
I must tell Soemon right away,
and introduce you to him.
Please do.
I'll go see if he's home.
Is he staying here?
He's been staying in
the cottage a few days.
He went to see someone
today and isn't back.
I'll give him the money
as soon as he returns.
You can meet him tomorrow.
He's been quite depressed lately.
This money will surely cheer him up.
You certainly did well
to make this 100 ryo.
"Wanted for Five Murders.
Reward for Information."
Oh, big brother!
Oh, you are back.
How is the house?
Thanks for taking care of us.
Don't thank me,
just pay the rent!
You're awful cold to
your little sister!
Business is business.
You've got something
interesting there.
How about a drink?
I've something to do first.
But get it warm
and I'll be back later.
He's always like that.
That's a load off my shoulders,
to get my father's forgiveness
after ten years.
Let's celebrate!
But I was really worried
he would ask how we got the money.
We could have told
him anything.
But us together in
peace is like a dream.
Look at his face...
Saké really tastes
great tonight.
But that night in
Fukagawa was scary!
But we got away!
I didn't think we would.
It was sad for the others.
Yes.
Kikuno died in place of me.
Don't talk like that.
You'll make the saké sour.
What would you do
if Gengobe showed up?
He wouldn't come here.
He's a wanted man.
Oh, he may be out
there watching us now.
Don't say things
like that!
I feel creepy!
If he shows up here, I'll take him
right to the authorities!
After all, he's a
wanted murderer.
Are you really as
brave as all that?
No, I'm really scared.
Why ruin a celebration
with talk like that?!
Good fortune has
finally come our way.
But I'm just not used
to happiness yet.
Our hard times did go
on for a long time.
Won't you please.
Take good care of me?
Don't cry. Let's cook,
and celebrate.
Go get some wood.
We didn't buy any.
Then rip off some paneling.
We should ask the landlord.
Silly! The landlord
Is your brother.
What's his is ours.
What's ours is ours.
Stop! I think
brother's come back.
Is it you, Brother?
Gengobe!
You two look settled in.
I'm happy for you.
Glad to see you well too...
Since we last met in Fukagawa,
I heard you had moved to this area
so I came to visit.
And I brought you
some saké as a gift.
Thank you.
Ah, come right on in.
You've got a nice place here.
Come right in.
Before there were all
sorts of mistakes...
You must be angry,
but we can explain it all.
Thanks for coming all
this way to visit...
Open that saké.
Oh, no, we couldn't
possibly drink it.
Remember that I am
the samurai Gengobe.
I don't hold any
grudge against Koman.
You mean you will
forget everything?
Just as water dries
as the days pass.
Don't worry.
I wish to continue being good friends
as we always were.
What welcome words.
Come anytime at all.
So open my saké and
let's drink to that.
As you say.
Relax and drink.
Oh, no, I insist you
drink mine tonight.
I have some warmed just right.
Pour him a drink.
Please have a drink.
I accept your hospitality.
This reminds me of the night
we first met in Fukagawa.
Koman, sing me a song,
like that night.
What're they up to?
This brings back memories.
It was all just a dream.
That was a dream, and
this is a dream.
The flower's red fades
like your love, and...
my sadness is like the
eternal flow of water.
Please sing one more.
What'll it be?
Oh, Gengobe, there was one
you always used to ask for,
wasn't there, Gengobe, sir?
You remember, Gengobe,
what was it, Gengobe?
Oh yes, it was
"Chrysanthemum Dew."
Will you sing it
for me, Koman?
"Victim Number Two"
This is the place.
You're sure?
Yes, there's no mistake.
He is definitely
Gengobe Satsuma?
Right. My reward?
You're a nuisance!
Nobody wanted your
information anyway!
But the poster said he was wanted
and promised a reward.
Put out your hand,
you noisy nuisance!
Oh, thank you.
But this is only
a tiny copper coin!
Things have gotten
noisy out front.
Oh, it's the neighbors.
Is Sangoro at home?
Yes. Just a minute.
Sangoro?
That is Gengobe,
the Fukagawa murderer?
Yes, it is.
You go back in and tie him up,
and bring him out here to me.
Not me.
You're the official here.
Go tie him up yourself.
If I could, I wouldn't
ask you to do it.
You can do it easiest
of us all.
That's not my job.
Please go on in.
What's happening here, Sangoro?
Are you Gengobe?
I am.
Did you commit those
murders in Fukagawa?
Sir, I am a ronin,
but still a warrior.
I do not kill women and children.
You have the wrong man.
But we have a witness.
A witness? Where is he?
That man there.
Oh, no, sir, not me. This is
the first I've even heard about it.
So Sangoro is
the witness against me?
Oh, no, not me.
I don't know anything.
Right. We know
nothing about it.
Is there any definite
evidence to prove.
Who the murderer is?
Yes, we have very
clear evidence.
Have you ever seen
this bodkin before?
That bodkin!
This is one of a pair
belonging to you.
This was at the scene
of the murders.
Clear evidence.
Let us tie you up.
Wait! You have
the wrong man!
He's not the
Fukagawa murderer.
What? Who are you?
Hachiemon!
What are you doing here?!
If that bodkin proves
who the murderer is,
then it is someone else.
It is not Gengobe.
You're protecting me?
Don't try protecting
your master! Move!
What man would protect
such a disloyal master?
Who do you say did
the murders?
It was me.
Do you have proof?
I do. I have the mate
to that bodkin.
This is certain evidence.
It is the mate.
But why did you kill them?
Koman and Sangoro
cheated Gengobe.
So I killed their cohorts, but...
I regret that
I didn't get them as well.
I have been trying to kill them
ever since that time.
I came out of hiding
when I heard that...
Gengobe was about to
be caught in place of me.
Please take me, the real murderer.
Tie me up and take me to prison.
Your story holds water
and you have evidence.
I arrest you for
the Fukagawa murders.
Tie him up!
Please let me suffer
the shame of arrest...
by having my own
master tie me up.
Me tie you up?
I will, but in my heart.
Don't waste your heart
on prayers for me,
but go join the others...
as a true samurai instead.
If only you do that,
I will be in heaven.
And so just forget
that beastly woman...
and don't let her
make you waver, sir.
Do only that for me, sir.
Tie up the criminal,
Gengobe!
Please tie me up, sir.
Forgive me.
I die happy.
Take him away!
Goodbye, my master.
And you two started all this!
Please forgive me.
Don't blame Koman.
Your anger is natural,
but I did it for him.
We're not even human,
please overlook us.
My servant's words
moved me deeply.
Koman, I give you up
from this moment on.
We thank you from the
bottom of our hearts.
Lift your faces.
If you're sincere, drink the saké
that I brought you.
Goodbye.
We're saved!
Quick, bring salt!
Out with the demons!
Let the good in!
That's a relief!
I thought any minute was going
to be the end, but here we are.
I'm so weak that
I can't stand up.
I thought we were
done for too.
Let's celebrate!
That's cold. Have
some that's heated.
That's a good idea.
To our happiness!
"Victim Number Three"
What a mess that was!
Come on in!
Is it all ready?
Have a drink!
Things would have been
bad without me.
I didn't know
you were here.
You really saved
our lives.
I saved your lives.
Have one more
as our gratitude.
Gratitude?
One drink isn't enough.
But Brother...
You think I don't know you took
100 ryo from Gengobe?
I know the whole story.
You're awful.
We don't have that money now.
You can't fool me like
you did him!
We know that.
But that money all went to our Lord
for a special purpose.
Who's that?
I've never seen him,
but his name is Soemon Funakura.
So you're Enya supporters?
That's interesting.
I'm a Kono retainer.
So that means we are enemies.
Oh, no, just my father
used to work for Enya.
Don't speak of us as
your enemies!
It's suddenly cold.
Koman, build up the fire.
Sorry I neglected it.
It has gotten cold!
That's the wall!
You'll pay for that!
Don't get so angry.
We forgot to buy wood,
and started using this.
Stop joking and use
what's under the floor.
Oh, is there some here?
Cheer up now.
Oh, it's all gone,
but there's more here.
Cold saké is just fine.
Oh, look what I found here.
What's this?
It looks like a floor plan.
A carpenter of the
Konos lived here.
A secret way into
the alcove.
A trapdoor on
the veranda.
This may be the Kono
mansion floor plan!
If it is...
This is a real find!
I won't let you keep it!
Please give it back!
What'll you do with it?
Stop it!
Brother!
Maybe in this saké...
You gave me poisoned saké!
Why would we do that
to you, Brother?!
He got what was
meant for us!
Then Gengobe!
Damn! This is a scheme
of the Enya family!
I'll pay you back
for all this!
Then it's the end for us.
I'm sorry!
Get away!
No, stop it!
Please...
Please, stop!
Don't look!
Close your eyes!
This is terrible!
Koman, I've killed your brother,
and now we're enemies!
There's nothing else
left for me to do!
Goodbye, Koman!
Let me die!
If you're going to die,
kill me first!
But if we die,
what will happen to our baby?
Settle down!
We can die any time.
Take this floor plan
to your father now.
We can die any time.
You're right.
I had forgotten this.
I'll be back in
a few minutes.
Wait a minute.
Take this just in case.
Right.
You clean up here.
Take care.
We'll never leave you
alone again.
You've had lots
of troubles too.
You were born under
a sad star.
Namu Amida Butsu.
What a terrible fate.
"Gengobe, at that time..."
Gengobe...
It's me, Gengobe.
So you didn't drink
the saké I brought?
Is Sangoro here?
No, he's out.
Out?
You're not lying, are you?
It's true.
You're always full of tricks.
"HELL"
So you have a son?
I didn't notice earlier.
It's clear who his father is.
He looks just like Sangoro.
You really made a fool of me,
with a son too, didn't you, Koman?
Oh no, I didn't make
a fool of you.
Your love was all
a planned trick.
Oh no, never that.
Then why, with a son and husband,
did you promise to be my wife?
And even your tattoo
pledge probably...
No. That tattoo...
Fake too? Let me see it.
"Precious Sangoro?"
Eternal proof of your treachery,
here on your arm for all to see.
You cheated me at every turn!
Forgive me.
I can explain everything!
No explanations!
That tattoo is clear proof.
I see everything clearly now!
I'll kill you and
Sangoro both!
A warrior, and I let
a woman do this to me?
Please forgive me
and let me live!
Then tell me where Sangoro is!
I don't know!
Tell me,
or this is what you get!
Shut up!
The child is innocent!
Then tell me!
I don't know and
wouldn't tell even if I did!
Stubborn woman, talk!
Your "Precious Sangoro!"
Is this the arm?
I'm ready to die! kill me!
I won't blame you for it,
but don't hurt my child!
Please don't take
the life of my child!
You want pity for him?
Then pity him by
killing him yourself.
Why did you think it's necessary
to kill my innocent child?!
A demon!
You're a demon!
A horrid demon!
It was you two who
made me a demon!
Die, Koman!
"This world is a sea of blood."
Sengoro, someone's coming.
You have committed murder.
Hide in that coffin.
And don't come out
until I tell you to.
I wanted to drink to
our future together.
But in your present situation,
that is no longer possible.
What a pitiful woman!
All you can do now is quietly
go on your way to Buddhahood.
When I gave that 100 ryo for you,
I was willing to give up
everything for you,
no matter what others
would say of me.
It was with that 100 ryo that I made
the most definite decision of my life.
All that's left now is eternal,
All enveloping darkness.
Is there anything else
where you are, Koman?
Is there true Godairiki
in that world?
Won't you say
something to me?
Answer me!
Who's there?
It's me, Tokuemon.
I have been waiting
for you to return.
Please look at this, Soemon.
What's this?
My son Sentaro and his wife
have come back,
after many trials
and tribulations.
My son killed his
wife's brother...
to get this floor plan
of the Kono mansion.
Soemon, please meet
my pitiful son...
and give him a word
of encouragement.
What do you mean,
giving these to me?
It's too late now.
What?
Hachiemon got me 100 ryo
which I used to ransom a geisha.
Then she cheated me and,
I killed many in hate.
I know I was a fool, but...
I am the man who committed
the 5 Fukagawa murders.
What? But...
Gengobe is the name
I have been using.
Hachiemon was arrested
in place of me.
I no longer have
the right or the desire...
to be counted among
the faithful retainers.
I only regret that
I let that rascal...
Sangoro get away alive.
Sangoro? That is my son
Sentaro's childhood name.
And I've heard
his wife was a geisha.
Does that mean?
This is my cloth,
so this 100 ryo!
Gengobe is Soemon?!
Sengoro!
Your anger is only natural,
but my son left home very young
and had never seen your face.
He knew you as Gengobe.
Please forgive my pitiful son.
We can forgive,
but Koman's life is gone.
Something happened to Koman?
Look! This is her head.
I killed both Koman
and her son too.
Sentaro!
Sangoro!
Goodbye, sir!
I killed Koman's brother.
I must die.
My wife and son are dead.
I have no desire to live
without them.
Wait!
Don't be hasty, Sentaro!
I don't want to hear
or see any more.
Even if there is sunlight,
this maggot can abide
only in deepest darkness.
I have lived a useless life.
Koman!
Soemon!
Namu Amida Butsu...
"Several months later..."
"the Enya retainers
carried out their vendetta."
"But Soemon Funakura
was not among them."